this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
c-radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society software Magazine
online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
I'm your host Jeff Doolittle I'm excited
to invite Dan Demers as our guest on the
show today for a conversation about data
collaboration and dataware dandemers is
co-founder and CEO of cinchi and a
Pioneer in dataware technology
previously he was an I.T executive at
some of the most complex Global
financial institutions in the world
where he was responsible for delivering
Mission critical projects Greenfield
Technologies and multi-million dollar
technology Investments after realizing
that half of all it resources were
wasted on integration he created sinchi
with a vision to simplify the Enterprise
and provide the rightful owners of data
with universal control of their
information Dan welcome to the show
thanks for having me happy to be here so
your bio seems to give a bit of a sense
of what dataware might be
so give us a brief introduction to what
dataware is and why our listeners should
be interested in it sure the easiest way
to understand dataware is to actually
just remind ourselves what is software
because there was a day where software
didn't exist and then it came into
existence and today we take it for
granted but so what did software do it
separated the form from function right
we had machines machines existed prior
to software host software though you
have machines but machines can then be
programmed which is the instructions the
logic I.E the software and that change
and transformed how you think about
machines right now from that point
forward the more programmable a machine
is the longer that machine is going to
last the more versatility is going to
have the more function it's going to be
able to be capable of doing because you
can defer that until after the
manufacturing process you know brilliant
major shift and change the world and
continues to change the world today well
dataware is really just the next step in
that inevitable decoupling and this time
it's not separating the a form function
it's separating the knowledge from the
function from the logic so it's
essentially decoupling data from the
software and that magically simplifies
everything quite frankly and it starts
with relieving software from all the
complexity of how to store data how to
integrate data how to share data how to
protect and Control Data and can now
allow the software to do what it was
originally intended to do which is
implement the functionality implement
the logic the actual program and let
dataware solve the data problem in the
same way that software lets Hardware
solve the physical Machinery problem so
what are some of the challenges that
people face in shifting first maybe
they're thinking from the current
Paradigm to what you're describing and
then after that maybe we can start
digging a little bit more into some of
the technical challenges but maybe first
start with sort of what does it take for
somebody conceptually to kind of
transition from you know the current
Paradigm to more of this dataware
approach that you're advocating right I
would say it's a really good question
and I don't know if I've even cracked
the code on on that in spite of giving
that a whole lot of time and energy
because it is both strangely simple and
complex and what I've come to realize
though is it's easier to explain the
concept of data where sometimes to a
child that has no you know existing
reference frame on how it works and I
learned that just even through
explaining it to my kids I got three
young boys and and their friends and
they would just kind of naturally get it
whereas someone who has you know 30
years of experience and has gone through
several iterations and understands data
lakes and data warehouses and data mesh
and data Fabric and all these latest
buzzwords dataware is hard for them to
get their head around and what I've also
come to realize is so it's an unlearning
Journey as much as it is a Learning
Journey but there's also just a lot of
almost like collateral damage from the
over hyping of data related Technologies
like if you go back to your data
warehouse and data Marts and data mesh
data Fabric and data virtualization and
master data management and you know each
of these things if you read the
marketing materials or the vendors when
it was coming out it sounds like it's
going to save the world right but it
doesn't it solves an individual problem
and sometimes even creates additional
problems so there's there's all this
noise of what we're really
false hype Cycles right that that
weren't major shifts software is the
last major shift right that that was a
big deal uh that genuinely changed the
world and continues to you know software
is eating the world and continues to but
dataware is the software that's eating
the world so it's a combination of
unlearning and making it feel practical
in a context that you understand that's
that's what I found but again I haven't
cracked the code so I don't know maybe
we can figure it out together I don't
know well then how does dataware relate
then to Applications maybe in a way
that's different from what's previously
been thought of well yeah so
traditionally applications are designed
to store their own data and it's not
because someone consciously said that
data should belong to an application
right no one ever decided that and then
architect technology to bring that
concept to life it was a it was like an
accidental design if you if you think of
the the evolution of uh software you
know the first computer programs as as
instructions didn't necessarily have the
context of a memory they couldn't
remember information right so if the
program was terminated and then you run
the program again they can't remember
where I left off and so the origins of
Digital Data was really to act as the
memory for that program
when we talk about kind of the state of
applications owning their data and maybe
that wasn't explicitly sought by teams
but the microservices movement from what
I can recall has actually explicitly
stated that Services should own their
data right so maybe explore that a
little bit in in regards to how does
dataware sort of fit in that mindset and
is it completely you know turning over
the tables of that concept yeah I think
you have to go back even prior to
microservices and prior to service
oriented architecture and all the
architectural shifts before that to
really get an understanding of the whole
thought behind why apps own data and you
alluded to it which is that was never
really originally an intentional design
it was an accidental design because the
you know the first computer programs
they would store Digital Data to act as
a memory for the program right so it was
in fact the data was subservient to the
program it was there to meet the needs
of the application right to remember
State and other such things but as the
application sort of more sophisticated
you know when Beyond Simple State
persistence and would have you know
business context business information
transactions information about a
customer so on and so forth but we never
really at the time had a need to rethink
the ownership of data so it still
continued to live in this Paradigm where
it's subservient to the application and
then suddenly woke up and realized that
that data has value so we we can mine it
but because it's siled in these
applications I can't you know that
minimizes my ability to extract value
from that data so that's when we attempt
to bring copies of it together in the
form of data Marts and data warehouses
and all the different variations you
know data Lake data virtualizations all
these are trying to solve that same
problem which is data's everywhere and
therefore it's nowhere so I need a
Consolidated view either physically or
virtually to be able to get the
intelligence out of that But continuing
to try and get a Consolidated view while
continuing to spin up applications that
create more data silos is obviously
you're chasing your tail and the the
shift from software from monolithic to
client server to three tier to end tier
to SOA to microservices there's a
phenomena there which is the scope of a
piece of software gets smaller over time
and that's how you achieve scale because
you can't scale because you can't
centralize everything you need to
Federate right so it's that Federation
so basically you have software that's on
a journey where what used to be one
application is now 100 applications and
you can call them microservices that
have a defined scope et cetera et cetera
but it continues with that model of
whatever your scope of software is
whatever the boundary is in the context
of a microservice the service boundary
is also your data boundary but which
microservice owns a customer such that
no other context outside of that service
would ever need to have any awareness of
customer like the whole thought quite
frankly if you take a step back is
ridiculous like how can data be owned by
an application State can be owned by an
application but business information it
just doesn't make sense if you were to
redraw the you know the entire landscape
ignoring all the current constraints and
historical constraints you would never
put data inside of the software it would
be a separate and distinct plane that
would also need Federation similar to
software and that's really what dataware
is doing is it's creating almost like
the data equivalent of an application
Network which is a network of connected
services with well-defined contracts but
doing that for data and doing it in a
manner that allows the software to
interact with that plane but neither is
subservient to the other they are two
separate Concepts you've got basically
logic and services and then you have
information and those are two completely
different things that obviously interact
with each other and it's not even just
one way sometimes the data can interact
with the service because for example I
can register a CDC listener on a piece
of data and then that can trigger some
type of business process which may
invoke a service
the sense I have is it's pretty Broad
and I think there's a few areas that we
can tackle here that we'll get to as as
the show continues you know there's a
lot of things going on in my mind right
now but what I want to lean into here is
you mentioned uh in your bio that I read
at the top of the show that in your
experience half of all it resources were
wasted on integration and so I feel like
we're getting closer to that as you're
describing all of these applications and
the data that's kind of locked in these
different silos and so share a little
bit of your experience about how you saw
that waste coming about and then help
explain how dataware has helped resolve
that situation I think back to when I
came out of school and I kind of
accidentally stumbled into the world of
large Global financial institutions and
I spent the first 11 years of my career
at Citigroup and you know a big
organization that's been in business for
200 years had 10 000 plus applications
and lots of mergers and Acquisitions and
I spend billions of dollars on
technology every year about 30 has
changed and me being part of that change
team whether I was enhancing or fixing
existing systems or consolidating
systems or building net new systems a
little bit of kind of all the above and
so doing that was an eye-opener because
you know throughout that decade new
technology was coming to Market that
allowed faster production of business
capability right with you know different
Frameworks uh new programming languages
so on and so forth but with in spite of
the fact that you could produce
functionality faster projects weren't
really getting delivered faster and you
can chunk the projects down and use an
agile based delivery but it just still
felt like it was getting slower and then
I had this realization where you know I
could pick up the phone and call any of
the thousands of developers and say what
are you doing right now and chances are
they're writing an API to basically
expose data or to access data or
building an ETL or doing a
Reconciliation or implementing some type
of after the fact government like
something that just is all because the
data is all over the place and that
percentage of time what I now call the
integration tax actually was getting
more expensive over time as the software
was getting more more focused and and
you know the evolution from monolithic
to to microservices and and you know
that wasn't an overnight thing it was a
gradual Journey more apps more silos and
those silos need to be destroyed and the
typical approach is to destroy them
using integration and but you're
integrating everything to everything
over time and that's just not
sustainable so that was easily consuming
half of the entire change budget of such
a large organization but what was even
more interesting is it was getting more
expensive as technology advanced and and
obviously that doesn't make any sense
like imagine if every day you show up to
work your income tax gets uh percentage
Point higher is going to be a point
where you stop showing up to work
right so something had to give right so
it didn't immediately hit me with the
actual it took a honestly it took a long
time to kind of extrapolate the the
symptoms into the underlying root cause
but I'm very confident that the nature
of data wear is basically the missing
thing that caused that that essentially
reverses that Trend and there's an
inevitability to it meaning just like
software if the person who invented the
first computer program was never born
somebody else would have written the
first computer program like it's it's
there's no question that it would have
happened it's kind of like have you ever
watched Terminator Terminator 2 Judgment
day like it's you can call it something
else you can delay it but it's going to
happen dataware is inevitable
yeah I think it was Ada Lovelace wrote
the first computer program if I'm not
mistaken so integration obviously as you
pointed out huge expense complexity on
top of complexity and essentially your
claim there is that it's hearkening to
this inevitability the data wants to not
be sort of confined within either
microservices software
yeah it's interesting too it triggers a
lot of patterns in my mind like I know a
lot of the DDD patterns relate to trying
to figure out how do you bound data
within context but then how do you share
the data between contexts and I've seen
that get incredibly complex and
Incredibly challenging as time goes by
you know why because that context
changes over time and sometimes you get
it wrong and you know if the world was
just fixed and never changed then in
theory you could design towards that
but it's Dynamic it changes the context
of today is not the context of tomorrow
and if you tightly couple your data
boundaries with your service boundaries
then you're going to be screwed and and
again just take the example of the
customer customer is not owned by a
single service right it's if I work in
an organization that's 10 000
applications how many do you think need
to know something about a customer
something about an employee something
about a product probably about ten
thousand yeah and maybe different things
that they accrete to that customer that
are contextual to maybe one or a few
services but not to all and yeah yeah
these various sorts of things
let's dig into one of the more specific
challenges that I imagine listeners
might be asking about right now that I
know I'm asking is there's data and
there's data so there's there's blobs
there are files there's relational data
stores there's document databases
there's all these different ways of of
storing and retrieving data so how does
dataware kind of deal with you know I
guess the struggle I'm having maybe
intellectually here is it feels like
somehow there'd be this monolithic
dataware platform to rule them all and
like to have to turn all my data into
some new format is this is this just
another integration that I have to do
like how does how does dataware kind of
deal with those kinds of challenges
right yeah no it's a good question and
you have to think of data wear in the
same way that you think of software
right there's not one piece of software
there's not one pattern of software it's
a whole new approach right to make
machines that can defer their exact
functionality to a program that can be
written later right that's essentially
what a software is and dataware is that
separation of data from the software and
you could Implement dataware through a
central monolithic platform you
absolutely could that's probably not
going to take you very far however you
could also Implement dataware as a
Federated network of information that's
properly governed using even DDD type
principles right where you're organizing
data into domains and and those domains
are business aligned as your business
changes and evolves you're you're
adapting your domains accordingly and
does it need to be a central platform it
could be a decentralized platform it can
so there's there's going to be good ways
there's going to be bad ways and there's
going to be an evolution in the ways
that data dataware comes to life but you
know dataware is data where when it is
separate and distinct from the software
and you also mentioned of you know the
different formats and protocols and you
know persistence Technologies like
document versus graph versus relational
versus you know uh columnar versus all
these different specialized formats put
that all Loosely in the bucket of data
of information whether it's structured
unstructured semi-structured and again
if it's separated from an individual
visual piece of software then you're
applying a dataware-based approach like
in my mind dataware configuration or
approach that would fit in a modern
Enterprise is one that basically draws a
line between the software and the data
and the interface is supporting polyglot
and multiple formats and you know
whether I want to interact with
something and benefit from the benefits
of like a document database to give me
schema flexibility or graph database so
I can use inference or relational
database where I want referential
integrity and transactions and and
whatnot these are just capabilities of
whatever I'm using to implement my
dataware layer whether I built that or
whether I bought that or whether I
bought a bunch of things and assembled
it to create a dataware environment but
again the core is that it's it's
separate the line is redrawn you've got
software applications and then you've
got data and they're independent things
that interface with each other but
neither is owned by the other that's
datawear so maybe down to brass tacks a
little bit if I want to get started on
doing some I mean maybe naively somebody
might say okay fine I have a postgres
database and my data is separate from my
application and heck I've been under one
application third and fourth application
okay so then I just naively give
everybody a connection to my postgres
database and say thumbs up I have
dataware so
database pattern we know that went well
right but tell us why that's not
dataware yeah and honestly that's a fair
question but it's kind of like if you
take let's use a let's switch context
for a second and let's use collaboration
technology for documents so like
everyone's use Google Drive or
SharePoint or box or OneDrive or
something that allows us to have a file
or a collection of files that I can give
access to other parties we can work
together on that it's Version Control
it's Access Control we're using
basically collaboration technology to
basically collaborate on files what's
the difference between that and say a
file system like why did I need
collaboration technology why did I just
give you access to my file system right
and it's well because quite frankly the
file system is missing collaboration
functionality it wasn't designed to do
that it's designed to basically organize
information in the context of a computer
right not in the context of like the
world so collaboration technology
basically adds in the missing
functionality to make that actually
viable because if you gave everyone
access to your file system trust me it
ain't gonna work right and we know that
the same is true with the database if I
give you access to my database well who
owns the data model right you go when
you muck with the data model and all of
a sudden I have code that was written
against that model and it breaks like
how dare you so you start to then want
to create silos as a result of that and
whether it's data model changes like
schema Evolution or if it's physical
resources and and whatnot you run into
all these problems it's well it's
because a database wasn't designed for
collaboration the intended use of a
database as we know it today was to meet
the needs of a single application it's
designed to be the servant of an app and
that's it you know end users business
users don't log into the database it's
just not designed to do that however
dataware and again there's there's
different ways that you can go about
implementing it at conceptual level it
is designed to do that it is designed to
enable collaborative data management
whether it's two applications whether
it's two development teams whether it's
two business teams or whether it's all
those parties all collaborating where I
can own data you can own data I can
reference your data but you can evolve
your schema independent from mine I can
grant access without you needed to get
copies of that you can interact with it
as a human as a machine as artificial
intelligence that's essentially what
it's doing so let's talk a little bit
about the dynamism that I think I just
caught there you talk about like schema
Evolution so that would be one of the
problems with sharing your there's many
there's please listeners I'm not
proposing you to share your postcode
connects with a bunch of other
applications that'd be really bad but
you talk about dynamism and schema
change so let's explore that a little
bit we'll get into it a little bit later
about like there's got to be some like
dataware platforms or something like
that to resolve these things because
otherwise it sounds like we could just
be telling our listeners well you just
need to do more etls and you need to
come up with more centralized data
stores and you need to come with these
kinds of things but let's let's first
talk a little bit about like the schema
Evolution like how does that because
obviously that's a big challenge
especially when talk about like
statically typed languages and things
like this where maybe they're expecting
the data to be in an exact certain shape
and if it's not then they have problems
how does dataware help with some of
those kinds of challenges of sort of the
dynamic nature of the schema of data
over time yeah and that's where
plasticity comes in so if you think
about how your brain works right you
learn new information you make
observations you go to sleep your brain
what does it do it reorganizes it's
adapting its structure it's structural
plasticity and without that capability
you and I both wouldn't be very smart
like if if our brain couldn't reorganize
itself through new experiences we would
know tomorrow what we knew yesterday and
we would have the intellectual
capabilities of of not even a newborn
child right like because our our model
can't change and if we limited it so you
can extend it but never refactor it
meaning you can't evolve it you can just
add append to it similarly you're going
to run out of physical space
right unless our brains are designed to
just continuously expand but then it
will be inefficient so there's a reason
why you know human intelligence requires
the evolution of structure the evolution
of schema and that same phenomena is
true in digital systems as well but in a
model where the data is owned by an
application and if you're another
application and you're trying to
interface with my data because I own it
if I'm the application but you're not
talking to the data directly you're
talking to the code you now create you
know this data contract right which is
your code needs to be compiled against
some type of standard that if that
standard changes if I rename a column or
something and that changes the external
service then your code is going to break
in accordance with that and that makes
sense in a world where the data is
behind the applications right but when
data is now front and center and it is
existing on a separate plane that just
doesn't cut it it you can't have these
rigid contracts you need the ability for
one business team to refer to
information in another business team and
for the even the structure itself
whether it's appending or refactoring or
deleting and what not to be able to
evolve independently without it breaking
my whether it's my data my data
structure or my application code and
this becomes a complex subject in terms
of how one actually goes about
implementing plasticity by where it
becomes possible is through that
standardization of that data layer right
the dataware environment is what makes
that possible because you're
intercepting all data related operations
through your dataware environment
through your dataware layer okay so the
dataware is then helping with this sort
you mentioned plasticity with schema
change over time is maybe another way of
looking at it and I guess the idea to
make it concrete is if I have an
application and and it's getting you
know it's integrated with a dataware
platform and there's a certain
shape of data that I'm expecting and if
something changes the data wear is going
to still support me getting the data in
the format that I'm used to now I might
opt in to change over time absolutely
but the dataware is somehow going to
ensure that I can still receive the data
in the format that I expect yeah I can
give you a really simple example because
again this can be getting into the into
the guts of it which is good but if we
go back to the file and document
collaboration example I don't know if
you've ever noticed this and like we use
Google Docs for document collaboration
although more and more we're treating
documents as data and we can use data
collaboration to ultimately render that
obsolete but that's a whole different
conversation so Google docs for a second
or Google drive because it's not just
documents it's files if I take a file
and I take it from my local computer and
I put it on Google Drive and then I give
you access to that well when I'm putting
it on Google Drive I'm organizing it
right I'm giving it a name I'm putting
it in a in a structure and that
structure may be contained in another
structure like you can have some folders
just like a file system it kind of feels
like it's organizing files file system
but then I give you access and let's say
you bookmark that document well what
happens if I go and I rename that
document or I move it around I
reorganize the folder so I take it out
of this folder put it into the parent
folder rename that folder and then
rename that file what happens to your
bookmark what do you what do you
actually think happens to that bookmark
well I'm actually looking at a Google
Drive doc right now and it has a really
nasty long hash of some sort that I have
no idea what it means but I'm guessing
it's a document unique identifier so
that way I can reorganize the location
of the document without affecting it and
you can change the name of it without
affecting my ability to access it that's
it so that's a really simple example of
you know if I were to apply the concept
of plasticity to document collaboration
now just extend that to data and there's
more complexities to it than that that's
very simplistic sure but there's a
perfect example of that right so it's
and without Google Drive being in the
middle that concept wouldn't have been
possible right it's the fact that it's
intercepting it has awareness of whoever
created the file how they organized it
to sign you know that guide et cetera or
however it's uniquely identifying it and
it's separately tracking how that file
with an immutable reference is organized
but in theory I could have that same
document in five different locations and
not have five separate copies of that
right because it can just be a symbolic
link it can be a pointer but none of
that would be possible without the
collaboration technology right so you
know that's what document collaboration
did for documents and it's it's amazing
no more my bookmark is broken did you
move the file it doesn't have right you
don't need to it just works that's how
data should be if I write code and that
code refers to data that is organized in
a model and you change that model let's
take a simple example where you just
append to it or you rename something and
there's other scenarios where if you
break things apart or you combine things
or you you move things from one
structure to another there's some pretty
complex scenarios but conceptually
that's what it's doing is it's how to
gracefully handle those scenarios and
give the the other party the experience
that they would expect knowing that you
have this unique opportunity to
implement plasticity because you are
implementing a dataware layer yeah I
like what you just said there about
essentially making it easier for the the
integrator maybe we don't call them that
in this world but you know the the idea
that I've well a collaborator yeah the
collaborator right and you know I've
been saying for a while now that a good
API is hard for the implementer and easy
for the integrator you know and that's
another way of saying technical empathy
it sounds like here what we're doing is
we're saying let's do the hard work of
of making it easier for the person who's
working with this data or platform
instead of having them have to carry a
lot of the burden of a lot of these
things around and we'll get into some of
these other things in a minute like
access controls and managing schema
change and things of this nature let's
lean a little bit then into before I do
want to talk some about security and
access control in a little bit but first
one of the things you mentioned in some
of the the documentation from some of
your websites is this thing called zero
copy integration and it kind of came up
this there a little bit with like Google
Drive what's interesting is though you
know anyone who's Google Drive
recognizes that you can download the
file and bring it to your local and you
can print it and change it or these
kinds of things and so I think there's
probably some interesting challenges
there as far as it goes with with
dataware as well especially as we talk
about things like you know security and
information control and things of that
nature and then that's also going to
bring in a challenge around things like
you know availability and latency so
speak to that if you can some about how
data wear you know addresses some of
these challenges and what what zero copy
integrate maybe means and maybe what it
doesn't mean sure yeah so zero copy
integration is as a standard that was
actually just recently ratified in
Canada not too long ago actually that is
now being taken internationally and
think of that as a design principle that
you're designing to minimize copies and
how are you doing that well you're using
dataware to enable data collaboration
again using Google drive as that simple
analogy it's very similar and if I give
you know five collaborators access to
that then it doesn't mean that they all
need five copies it also doesn't prevent
them as you say right but there's
there's definitely fewer copies as a
result of collaboration than there would
be otherwise so that's a step in the
right direction because today the world
Works off of copies you know software
and developers are giant data copying
engines right that's all we do and
that's not going to instantly stop and
you have existing copies of existing
data inside of existing systems that's
also not going to be untangled anytime
soon right so it's really just changing
it such that on a go forward basis
you're consciously minimizing copies
because every copy is inefficient every
copy is compute it's storage it's it's a
potential transformation where you need
to do a Reconciliation there can be a
loss or corruption there's a loss of
control over that copy there's so many
bad things about copies that you want to
minimize that and the enablement of a
true like puristic World of zero copies
honestly it's not going to happen in our
lifetime but I can tell you confidently
that a world where you are forced to
copy every time you want to do something
as we traditionally are is also not a
world that is going to be sustainable so
it is it's all about the minimization of
copies and you'll find that over time
this is just a prediction at this point
is this going to be innovation in the
data wear space that will enable us to
get ever and ever closer towards
realizing that true zero the vision of
of the future yeah that's helpful so
zero copy doesn't mean there can't ever
be a copy under any circumstance but it
does mean that the goal is to minimize
the number of copies yeah and if you
read the standard it talks about that
because you have existing systems you
already have exactly copies and no
organization has time to re-platform
their entire ecosystem this is not going
to happen right so if you asked a
question earlier that I don't think we
answered which is how do you actually do
something about this when you already
have existing stuff right if you're
starting Green Fields then in theory it
would be easier but you're not you have
existing systems you've got modern SAS
apps you've got you know hybrid
multi-cloud you've got all this
complexity already well accept the fact
that your existing complexities that are
already implemented are already
implemented right it's already done
you've already eaten that complexity the
opportunity really is to change how you
deliver change going forward such that
if I'm going to build five new systems
let's say over the next year and all
these five systems need to interact on a
common concept maybe they're adding
information related to a customer or
something rather than each of these five
having their own slices of this
information and then doing Integrations
between them apis etls and adapting it
to application specific data models that
may evolve over time but but you get
into the contract things instead make it
so that these five applications can
collaborate on that and do it in a way
that doesn't have all the byproducts and
downsides of you know a shared database
right in other words proper data wear
technology and now instead of five
copies you can have just the one
original copy for those five
applications and that's that's a very
simple example but it's it's really just
changing how you deliver change to use
collaboration versus iteration so if I'm
going to create a new PowerPoint
presentation rather than you know
creating a local PPT file and then
sending you a file attachment over email
as I would have done pre-document
collaboration I'm going to use some type
of collaboration Tech and I'm just going
to give you access you know that so
that's what zero copy integration is is
use collaboration as your default
approach for implementing digital
systems so how does that work when we
live in a world of the fallacies of
distributed computing so you know the
fallacy that the network is available
and that's reliable these kinds of
things does that prevent us from ever
reaching the Nirvana of a true zero copy
future right now I would say it does
through Innovation over time
maybe it we can overcome those barriers
and hurdles I can't tell you exactly how
but I personally wouldn't be surprised
if future Innovations in the dataware
space unlock that but definitely now
like today you're going to need to
implement caching you're gonna have to
account for you know Network latency
there's going to be other considerations
especially when you're dealing with like
transactional data and you know High
volumes like again I come from a
background of financial services so if
you're doing like high frequency Equity
trading where you're hypersensitive to
latency you've got to be aware of that
and that needs to be accounted for in
your design so however it's still good
to have collaboration even if you need
say local caching and the local caching
has eventual consistency back into the
original source and it's only trusted
once it's committed back right so
there's there's ways that you can still
move toward the minimization of copies
and work within the current constraints
of Technology
yeah and then I think about other things
like offline type approaches you know I
mean git is a great example of the
ability to collaborate in a distributed
fashion and then you reconcile after the
fact and then there's as we're talking
about Google Drive and Google Docs you
know conflict-free replicated data types
crdts I'll put a link in the show notes
that's another one of these mitigating
Technologies you could possibly use to
handle partially connected types of
scenarios and I imagine and I've seen
you nodding so I'm like okay it seems
like these could be relevant things
going forward to be able to help with
zero copy Integrations yeah for sure
because one thing to keep in mind is
like we have through my company we have
a dataware platform but again dataware
is not such that you need to use a
singular platform there's lots of you
can Implement your own you can assemble
it using different Technologies but when
we've designed our platform we kind of
think of it that way which is it's like
a git for data and that includes
metadata of course and not only the
ability to you know have multiple
branches and merging and like all the
functionalities that you would expect
and you know
in a modern such tool but extending that
to the world of data but it gets really
interesting when you think of even the
time machine aspects of what dataware
makes possible because again by
introducing a universal data layer that
has awareness of schema Evolution and
data Evolution over time it also unlocks
that potential right to creatively use
the awareness of the historical
evolution of schema such that you can
now run queries and pull data from the
past in the model of the past and so it
opens up all these interesting things so
you start to realize that it opens up
the if I can go back into the past like
in our platform I can run a query in the
past and I can see it in the current
data model or in the model that was in
place at that time but I can't change
data in the past so we're starting to
think about what if you could change
data in the past what does that do okay
it spawns a timeline right and that
timeline was it always there and now
you're just revealing it or is it
actually creating it and it kind of gets
some of these more advanced scenarios
get pretty damn complicated but the fact
that they're even possible is exciting
it's not just a matter of time before
solving them all yeah I wonder if I'm
the only one now when you say alternate
timelines who's thinking about like you
know Biff Tannen and Back to the Future
and the alternate timeline you know we
got to get back to the other timeline
yeah that's interesting so you mentioned
the idea of dataware as a platform and
you just mentioned one aspect and let's
explore some of the other ones so
there's a few we're talking about you
know I want to talk a bit more about
access control and security but you just
mentioned one which is like this Dynamic
temporality which I think is something
new that hasn't come up previously in
our conversation
what factors generally I just mentioned
a couple but what characterizes data
where broadly you know it's more than a
postgres database where you share your
connection string with the world we get
that it's not application data locked in
silos it's not just you know a bunch of
etls and transforms you mentioned
metadata so can you sort of break down
what are the elements of a dataware
platform broadly we mentioned a couple
but maybe there's more yeah and one
thing to think about there and I should
have said this earlier is when you think
of for example that temporal kind of
superpower and the the ability to have
granular controls which we haven't
talked about but I'm sure we will and
these are all different capabilities
that can be built into a dataware
platform or not right so it's not
necessarily mandatory and there's going
to be you know different pros and cons
of one data where configuration and
architecture and pattern and platform
versus another so that's one thing to
keep in mind right is however what
dataware has that defines it to be
dataware is the fact that it is managing
data independent of software and the
enablement of that the coupling is the
very definition of what dataware is is
really doing right so you've got
software and software then sits atop
dataware and dataware provides
essentially everything that the software
needs in terms of data management how to
access it how to store it how to protect
it how to track changes to it all these
things is what it's providing really as
a service to not just one piece of
software but any piece of software so
that's what dataware is doing and then
there's basically features of a dataware
platform and that can include for
example the creation of that time
machine and what's interesting though is
it goes from like in a world where every
application is a data platform it would
never be economical for you to build
into that data platform for an
individual application all of these
superpowers right granular data level
data driven access controls a schema
Evolution support you know
multi-timeline and you know support
Wormhole queries which are like remove
time as a filter like you would never be
able to do this right just when your
simple application that would have cost
you ten thousand dollars is not going to
cost you 10 million dollars right you
can't do that but when you start to
concentrate into a common capability
that then gets used many times it gives
you that scale it's kind of like the
power grid if you think of you've got
power plants like nuclear solar
geothermal and they all have pros and
cons they all have different formats and
protocols and pros and you know they're
very complicated things but that's why
you know then there was a point where we
could generate power and there was no
power grid so what did the power grid do
well it basically decoupled the
producers of energy from the consumers
of energy that's basically what it did
is I could have solar panels on my roof
I can self-supply and then if I have
Surplus I can feed that back into the
grid and when I'm short I can draw down
from the grid and when I'm drawing down
maybe I'm grabbing it from you know the
solar panels from someone else who is
still under the sun well it's a cloudy
day where I am right and I don't even
necessarily need to know right because
it's all standardized for this and the
power grid provides all these
capabilities and it's still evolving
today like today's power grid is not
yesterday's grid and tomorrow's grid
will be even smarter right it's it's
evolving independently from Individual
power generation right but if we
identify a new way of generating
electricity maybe we can just harness
gravitrons and suddenly we can you know
whatever we can in theory just connect
that into the grid and I can still plug
in my iPhone and charge it right it's
that decoupling that's magical that's
all dataware is doing it's it's the
power grid for information management so
what that means though is that all the
different capabilities you have to make
sure that it fits your purpose right is
if you're building a dataware platform
you don't want to over engineer it you
don't want to under engineer it you want
it to be fit for purpose so you have to
actually figure out what requirements
you actually have to have a data layer
that spans applications that provides a
human interface for regular business
users to interact with it what are the
features you actually need I can tell
you the features that I need in my
environment but they're going to be
slightly different than what you might
need
so in a sense I guess it sounds like
dataware is it's like it's a form of
software I mean somebody's got to write
this software to provide these
capabilities but generally speaking it
seems like what it's doing is it's
decoupling the data the data management
the data access controls and then this
temporality as you said it sounds like
that's one of those things it's like it
sounds pretty cool by the way I mean you
know I could try to go back and Event
Source everything from scratch but good
luck that's a non-starter because the
data's already shredded into relational
tables but whatever but this ability to
do this temporality but broadly speaking
it sounds like it's a shift in here
we're writing software that's explicit's
purpose is not to solve this particular
business use case it's to solve this
data collaboration case and then the
business case can be provided by an
application on top of that and one of
the challenges
right and the challenge is if I'm
building a simple application building a
data where platform is going to be
excessive
Yeah by like a million times yes but if
I can leverage them as especially in
bigger environments so let's talk about
that a little bit too like there's a lot
of tools and Technologies out there to
try to simplify the integration burden
and I won't name any vendors but
listeners might be familiar with
companies who basically say hey just
plug all your data sources into us and
then we'll let you create these complex
workflows that shuttle the data around
to all these different places and
dataware seems like a different approach
to that so how does it differentiate
from maybe some of those other more
integration based approaches yeah well
I'd say you can kind of draw vendors and
technological approaches and whether
they're you know open source projects or
closed Source or internal proprietary
approaches or whatnot into one of two
categories it's either facilitating
better faster cheaper integration or it
is enabling the minimization of
integration so it's either a pro
integration or anti-integration
technology
what's kind of interesting and this
causes confusion is so why would I want
to do in integration is because I want
connectedness and reuse of data why
would I want to use anti-integration IE
collaboration well it's because I want
connectedness of my data so the ultimate
end goal of having data be organized in
a connected way is a universal need
right everyone wants their data to be
integrated the question is do you want
to integrate shun or collaboration which
is just you know which path gets you to
that end goal of connectedness of data
but I think you can largely put a
technology either into its facilitating
integration or it's facilitating the
avoidance of integration and on the
surface some of the promises may sound
similar but as the industry matures I
think you're going to start to be able
to more clearly differentiate you know
those who are in favor versus those who
are against integration as the pattern
okay so if I'm somebody who's writing
software and I want to explore data
where you know I imagine like any other
software I have to to integrate with
there's going to be some set of apis
that I'm going to be interfacing with
and then for end users it sounds like
there's going to be some I don't know
ability to maybe explore and see yeah
yeah so share a little bit with our
listeners about what is the human
interface on top of dataware yeah what's
interesting is the human interface and
the machine interface or the application
interface or the code interface whatever
term you want to use they actually share
similar characteristics in terms of how
they're powered and how they're powered
is through metadata so if you think of I
don't know I'll use just a relational
Paradigm just to simplify the
conversation if you have like a table
and I designed the model of that table I
give it a name and I give it some
columns and these columns have a
particular column type and whatnot well
that structural data which is also
available as data itself that gives you
the model right the schema I could
generate an end user experience or
generate an endpoint whether it's a soap
endpoint or resident point or expose a
via graphql or whatever future standards
emerge it doesn't matter and I can have
that endpoint that experience whether
it's an HTML interface or anything it
doesn't matter be adaptive based on the
metadata right and that's very simple
because it's just taking the structure
but add in the dimensions of the
controls add in the temporal
capabilities and all the other
considerations basically what you're
doing is you're harnessing metadata to
build hyper adaptive experiences whether
it's for humans or for machines that
adapt dynamically to the metadata such
that if I go in and I don't do something
as simple as rename an attribute of an
entity then the screens should adapt
themselves accordingly and the Machine
interfaces which maybe you're exposing
it as you know Json over rest should
also adapt accordingly and if I have
plasticity enabled such that I may be a
program interacting with the rest
endpoint getting the Json back where I
assumed a certain model and you have
awareness of who I am or I can honor
that out and respect that and be able to
track and basically prevent you from
breaking your code I could even do the
same for a human as well right so I can
insulate even humans from the dynamism
of schema Evolution so the mechanics of
of how you activate metadata to build
these interfaces dynamically is is
actually quite the same it's just what
is the actual end experience right is is
it an HTML interface is it a mobile
experience is it an AR experience a VR
experience is it a rest experience is it
these are all just now experiences so
that's that's what you have to think of
you know applications are really
experiences that will interface with
data and add of course logic around that
but the experience is still part of the
software right it's not part of the
dataware does that make sense I think so
let's talk a bit about Access Control
Management because I think that's a
significant challenge with a lot of what
we're trying to do with data and so in a
data you know you mentioned metadata
which that's unfortunately it's a very
meta concept like metadata could be
literally anything but I imagine one
aspect of the metadata is you know how
are we doing controlled access to the
data and how does that kind of shape out
in this dataware landscape yeah and I
think again the opportunity of having a
standard layer that separates software
from data meaning multiple applications
uniquely opens up the ability to have
consistency of controls right and the
ability to have the controls be enforced
in the data itself if you think of the
traditional approach where you have
individual apps that each solve
different business capabilities and they
all have their own local data store in
their own local data model and you're
transforming it from one app to another
where there's basically separate copies
of that even if it looks a little bit
different it's you know it's a
derivative of therefore it's it has
elements of the problem with that
approach approaches the controls and I
don't mean things like authentication or
even high level authorization I mean
like whose salary can I see as a simple
example right if I have salary data in
50 applications well whose salary can I
see imagine I have some level of access
to these 50 applications and some of
these could be operational systems some
could be analytical systems some could
be reporting you know maybe I can access
a tableau report or a click report or an
app or an API that all interface with
separate copies of this data like how do
I ensure that I can't see my boss's
salary or I can't change my own salary
or if I well that might be a feature not
a bug
yeah exactly so it's one of those things
that until you take a step back and
realize it's actually just impossible to
have consistency of controls in any
organization of any complexity which is
pretty damn scary and this is you know
someone coming from a background of
financial services where you know if
you're a customer dealing with a bank
know that the bank not because they're
dumb not because they're are trying to
screw you they have hundreds probably
thousands of copies of your data and
they're trying to control it but they
can't like it's it's like there's a
reason why a bank vault has one door not
a thousand doors and they'll just add a
new door every time you want to take a
deposit or a withdrawal right it's you
need to have that ability to have the
controls be defined ones and universally
and Forest and again that's separating
data from applications where you can
have many applications collaborating on
data is the opportunity to move the
controls from the application code into
the data itself so now that simple
salary example is a data policy that
says and different organizations will
have different rules maybe some have an
open policy where everyone can see each
other's salary but imagine a rule that
says you could only see the salary of
yourself or anyone who works for you
either directly or indirectly and as you
move through the organization maybe you
get promoted or demoted or I change
departments Etc that's all adapted
that's all Dynamic it's and whose salary
can I change well I can't change my own
salary but I can change the salary of my
direct reports but maybe I can only do
that when comp season is open and maybe
we do an annual comp review unless
there's an exception process like all of
these rules can now be expressed such
that they're applied and then forced in
the data such that it doesn't matter
which of the 50 applications I'm
interfacing with the controls are
guaranteed to be the same and if I write
a buggy application and the buggy
application says here I'm going to give
you this person's salary that you
shouldn't have because I'm kind of dumb
and I didn't know that you're not
supposed to see that well it's not going
to work because it's not running out of
the applications credentials it's
running under your credentials and you
don't have access to that which is a big
difference instead of apps having
service accounts to application specific
databases right where the app code has
unconstrained access to all data in that
database is it's all running under the
credentials of whoever the ultimate end
user is be that a system or a person
interesting so if I'm understanding that
correctly then the application would
always be executing on behalf of the end
user and that way the credentials that
are passed to the dataware would be the
users or this I mean it could be a
system but it wouldn't be this
application itself some type of identity
whether that identity is an artificial
human or a genuine human it is running
under the identity and that identity has
credentials and those credentials change
over time and those credentials should
be configured by whoever ultimately owns
the underlying data that is being
protected sounds like it would be pretty
important then to also be able to do a
couple of things one audit those access
controls and to be able to do that
independently directly with the dataware
platform sounds like a pretty pretty
important thing and then also the
ability to test and make sure that your
access permissions and control so maybe
speak to that a little bit about how our
existing or future dataware platforms
going to address those kinds of concerns
as well yeah well the way that we've
handled that in ours and I don't know if
they're in theory there could be other
ways of doing it but is we simply treat
the Control Data like those grants as
data and similarly they are under the
protection of dataware right where it's
all version controlled is access
controlled so who has access to the
access data right right and having the
granular control over that and the
temporal nature and the ability to have
the insulation basically data plasticity
and schema plasticity and all these
other considerations adding that to your
Control Data because at the end of the
day it's just data right is the ultimate
safety net because it gets into
interesting scenarios that you have to
design your policies around for example
in that salary analogy if I change
departments when I go back into the time
machine can I see the salaries of the
people who worked for me in the past and
this is all what's interesting is
dataware will force you to ask yourself
some questions that you'll need to
answer but you never would have even had
this question before because you weren't
even able to do these type of things
right so it gets quite interesting when
you have some more complex scenarios but
it's powerful because you can choose as
the owner of data what you want that
experience to be but but I think this
simple answer and I think you'll find
this as a common consideration of any
dataware implementation is that the
protections that you've put for business
data you're extending that to all other
forms of data about that data via
control be it structure be it
description be it you know any other
metadata it's just data so let's switch
gears a little bit there's a concept in
computer science that's been around for
decades and this sounds like it's going
to blow it up so speak a little bit to
the idea of encapsulation and
information hiding because my challenge
is as I look at this and maybe it's
still relevant maybe it still applies
but I'm wrestling a little bit with how
you know Real World Systems like we
don't have a conversation by cracking
opener skulls and connecting our neurons
and our axons that are dendrites that
would be dangerous and gross and painful
and all the other things and so how is
dataware not that and I I don't think it
is that but I mean I don't know because
I mean in my experience systems that
don't do a good job at information
hiding tend to be incredibly complex and
impossible to maintain and so help us
with the nightmare scenario that people
might meet like me might be thinking
about when we say oh my gosh we're just
going to connect everything to
everything now
um well actually the analogy that you
gave is perfect because you and I have
separate brains and that's not an
accident that's an intentional right
design right and there's the concept of
a collective intelligence which I think
for a long time people thought that's
where we were trending towards right
where you have basically the central
source of all knowledge and everyone can
just kind of hook into that in that type
of a model though the eventuality is it
becomes the Borg if you ever watch Star
Trek right where the agents are Mindless
they have no autonomy they have no
independence of thought right they are
simply agents of the collective but
that's not how it works in nature and
Nature's amazing at flushing out you
know the efficient model and it's not a
collective intelligence there's no
single Central brain it's a
collaborative intelligence and
collaborative intelligence requires
autonomy right coming back to why you
and I have separate brains yet we're
able to collaborate but you can choose
as the owner of the information inside
of your mind what information you want
to hide versus what information you want
to release you can tell tell me your
deepest darkest Secrets or you cannot
right that's your choice as an
autonomous being dataware is essentially
embracing that same Paradigm and
extending that to the world of digital
systems right where you can have whether
it's different business domains
different owners different individuals
all similarly having that ability to
hide information I.E manage access
controls but that's a little bit
different than what you were asking
which is the reasons why one would want
to encapsulate both logic and data in
the traditional world of software where
software traditionally owns both the
logic as well as the data I'm thinking
as I'm answering your question here is
it's an interesting question actually
but what's the answer part you answered
part well maybe you answered all of it I
mean generally speaking the idea of you
hearken to collaboration as opposed to
centralization you know we're not
talking about the one dataware database
to rule them all like
and that you know as you mentioned
Nature's done a fantastic job of
encapsulating things where they need to
be and I guess that brings to the idea
that there will be data where speaking
to dataware I guess is what I'm hearing
you say I'm having a conversation right
now and we're I'm seeing a bunch of
pixels on my screen and I'm hearing
sound coming out of my speakers and you
know we can collaborate and we're using
a language called English and and
there's there's you know the dataware
equivalent in the real world is is quite
complex I don't even really understand
it myself it's magical of it and it
allows us to have this conversation and
not only that it allows us to even pass
information not direct from people to
people but even across masses of people
and generations of people right like you
don't have to make a fire but you were
not born with that knowledge how did you
know that no human was born with a
knowledge of how to make fire you know
how to make fire It's Magic right and
that like how is that possible right one
thing that I always refer back to and
it's almost like I've come to accept it
just as a design principle is well how
does nature do it and if you want to
know the future of technology it's right
in front of you it's all around you it's
have you digitize the real world and
that is the inevitable future of the
digital equivalent of that real world
right
and there's lots of let's say design
inspiration to borrow from and
collaborative intelligence and
collaborative autonomy and the concept
of dataware is just an example but it's
a really good example yeah it reminds me
of something one of my mentors says a
lot which is that features are aspects
of integration not implementation
and what you're describing here is a lot
of potential integration points between
dataware platforms of various
capabilities and then the features can
emerge from those Integrations just like
you mentioned you know we're having a
conversation here right we didn't evolve
specifically to have a podcast there's
no feature you know in human evolution
to have a podcast but what we're doing
is we're integrating these various
things together so that we can create
something that didn't previously exist
not that no podcast has ever done before
but the concept of that is an
integration of different capabilities
and then emergent is the feature itself
so yeah and there's no Central Storage
of Dan's information and Dan's brain and
your information in your brain that
meets the needs of this specific podcast
right are there emerging protocols or
things you know I imagine the ability
part of this sounds daunting as you
mentioned you know like no small startup
team should be building well I don't
maybe they should but again if they're
trying to build a simple you know
application they should not be building
the dataware platform but you know what
kinds of like I don't know are there
emergent protocols or commonalities that
are coming out of it because I imagine
there's going to be competition in this
space as well and different ways of
doing things so what's kind of the
landscape in that regard yeah and it's
it's the early days for sure if you just
think of you know software's been around
for a while and it's continuing to
evolve and so dataware it is early days
however there is dataware platforms like
we have a dataware platform that you can
buy and you can use you can buy other
technologies that have similar
capabilities and they might work even
better for you in different contexts but
yeah as a startup if you're trying to
solve a particular you know you're
building an app for that you don't want
to be building a dataware platform at
the same time
so to your question though around
protocols and standardization and
whatnot so zero copy integration is an
example of a standard now that standard
though is not a protocol right it
doesn't describe exactly how to
technically implement it it really
describes the framework that one would
use to evaluate whether you are adhering
to that standard or not that is agnostic
to the technology implementation so yeah
it is something that I know we're
planning to do through the alliance is
to collaboratively create standards in
that space what you are seeing though is
if you take data mesh as an example like
there's a lot of hype around data mesh
which is basically borrowing domain
driven design from software architecture
and applying it to basically your data
analytics infrastructure to avoid the
creation of a monolithic data warehouse
and you know breaking the warehouse into
these different data products that are
organized into different domains and
you're seeing that go from a theory to
talking about the people and process
side of it to now the emergency of
technologies that claim to implement
this and again that's narrowly focused
on the analytics plane but you're seeing
like real technology bringing some of
these principles to life so I think the
stage that we're at right now is you're
having individual vendors having their
own spin on it and the problem with that
is it doesn't enable interoperability
between dataware environments right if
you built a data product in a mesh type
context to serve analytics and I have a
different dataware platform my ability
to seamlessly interface with yours
requires us to do guess what integration
that's right right so I'm now
integrating my dataware platform to your
dataware platform now that's still a
much better world than integrating every
application every application so it's a
step in the right direction it's kind of
like the evolution of networks when you
know we didn't start off in the first
Network wasn't the internet right the
internet is actually a network of
networks the network had to come first
that's kind of where we are in the world
is we have Networks but if you remember
the early days you got token ring and
ethernet and then even before that there
wasn't even like it's kind of like those
early days and that being said you know
I can choose to buy an Ethernet and
token ring and maybe I can't Bridge them
together or I can choose to have all my
computers be working in isolation and
not even have a network right that's not
a good choice
so that's kind of like I don't know does
that help no absolutely it's going to be
messy is what I'm hearing but that
doesn't it doesn't mean it's not the
right trajectory and you can't sit on
the sidelines like it's not going to
work because your competitors who take
advantage of this whether they build or
they buy or they do a hybrid or or
whatnot they're going to have a lot less
of that integration tax to slow them
down and how do you beat your competitor
that is able to do things in a fraction
of the time like it's not going to work
at scale anyways outside of some anomaly
so again there is an inevitability to it
we'll all be using dataware if you're
not already starting but today it's a
way of differentiating and giving one a
competitive Advantage but it very
quickly pivots to becoming an
existential requirement right like try
running a business today without
software whether it's Apple service or
not just don't use software use pencil
hey look yeah not many businesses are
going to be conducive to that anymore I
mean even you go to the farmer's market
and they all have you know some payment
Gateway attached to their phone and so
even their use and I you guarantee they
got a spreadsheet some Google sheet
somewhere managing their inventory and
their materials and stuff like that so
yeah yeah so good luck for leading the
world data where it's the software
dataware eats the software interesting
well it sounds like it's going to be
interesting days moving ahead as people
start exploring more of data wear and
then integrating dataware dataware and
you know emerging patterns are going to
come out of this and I imagine as you
said eventually we got to the network of
networks and very frankly it also it's
retained some of the words from the
previous and maybe that will be the case
here too but hey it's good enough it's
working so we're we're running with it
and it sounds like a similar thing could
happen with dataware yeah and that's why
we created the alliance the data
collaboration Alliance is to for parties
that are interested in learning more
about this as well as participating and
contributing to the establishment of
standards and you know the early days of
the emergency dataware ecosystem But
ultimately working backward from that
future that's all standardized it's all
interoperable and you know it's access
not copies based people have control
over their data that's why we created
that organization and while we're
working with data privacy experts from
across the globe as the initial members
but yeah this is kind of thing that's
going to be very very exciting for some
people scary for some other people but
for me it's exciting do you envision a
world where so for example we talk about
access not copies and then of course you
know what if you can't access the copy
because the network is down to these
kinds of things but yeah yeah you know
one of the challenges with these kind of
things too is like man in the middle
attacks or Bad actors in the system that
don't follow the rules right so I mean
in my ideal scenario let's take like my
personal health care information and a
great world would be a future world
where I bring that data with me and I
own that data my doctor doesn't own the
data my insurance company better not own
that data the government better not on
that data like I own that data and
ideally I bring it with me data is
irrelevant you mean to have control
control over the ownership of the data
that's right but now the ability to
revoke that control is where I see a
challenge here maybe you can speak to
that a little bit so I give my doctor
access I can't stop them for copying it
and so you know how are the
conversations shaping up in the dataware
space about challenges like this yeah so
it's interesting because even if you use
Google Drive as an example like I can
turn on settings that prevent you from
downloading copies of that but there's
going to be ways around that and quite
frankly if the screen is shown on as
pixels I can take a picture of yeah and
then you can OCR with a machine learning
AI yeah there it is again it gets harder
with Innovation right it doesn't get
easier it gets harder and the same is
true in the data world world so first of
all without that approach everyone is
forced to create copies of that where
those copies even if they're not
choosing to make a copy because they
want a copy maybe they don't have Mal
intent it creates the byproduct that can
be the source of a breach right because
you know the very presence of the copy
even if they don't want it is itself
giving some risk right so the reality is
your doctor probably just wants you to
get better it probably doesn't want to
steal all of your your data they
probably just literally need access to
be able to give you the right
prescription and they probably don't
care to see it after that so for the
most part like that's going to
dramatically reduce the risk and
exposure but the the absolute guarantee
and Assurance of that is kind of like
even money and intellectual property in
humans like these are all things that
have value and therefore we prohibit
copies of them it's illegal if I copy
money I can go to jail but guess what if
I was smart and I did a bunch of
research and I decided I didn't care if
I went to jail I could probably find a
way to copy money but it's not easy it's
hard and it gets harder over time right
it's and if I copy intellectual property
if I clone humans right it's these are
things that you know but the the
difference here is that these things are
already recognized as being of value and
respected as such whereas data we say it
has value but traditionally we haven't
respected it as such we don't even try
to do this right so there's absolutely a
future where the copying of data will be
illegal that's not anytime soon but that
is guarantee that's the future and does
that mean that data will never be copied
sadly no some people break the law okay
yeah there will always be counterfeiters
but there's ways that make it more and
more challenging over time yeah I still
am going to call you a counterfeiter
don't call them a good citizen if that
makes any sense yeah well and maybe part
of the future is where the network
itself might need to take on aspects of
dataware enforcement and things and that
isn't to say that somebody couldn't
fudge with the network and mess with
that but you know it could imagine if
you could create a network that you
could check and make sure it hadn't been
tampered with and you know there's all
kinds of implications
right so there's lots to be invented and
innovated on in this space so this is
just the beginning of the Revolution
this is not the end of it so more
questions than there are answers yeah
like maybe it's not zero copy maybe it's
few copies but if those copies are under
the control of a system that knows when
it must Purge it must you know rescind
and it must whatever and again now
you've passed the buck to some extent
but yeah you know that may be a way to
help mitigate some of these well you
know if there's only one copy literally
on a thumb drive plugged into somebody's
MacBook and you know in Uruguay and it's
illegal to copy it that's gonna be a
problem for some use cases and so you
know opportunity to innovate and explore
and possibly see what might come up
there so before we wrap up tell us a
little bit about your company cinchy and
kind of how dataware fits with what you
guys are doing yeah so we're all in on
dataware so what we're really doing is
we're building a platform that
organizations can use to basically
bootstrap their data transformation and
change how they deliver change
and so we've been working on that for
five six years now and been growing a
business and we have some good
Enterprise customers using it but we're
also committed to just accelerating that
inevitable shift to dataware which is
why we also have the data collaboration
Alliance that while we started it's an
open not-for-profit that anyone can join
and contribute to to work
collaboratively on standards that of
course since she has a for-profit
company is very committed to adhering to
right because we're trying to create the
acceleration of this future and it's not
going to work if there's only one day to
wear platform right that's not the
future but yeah so we're used by mostly
mid and large Enterprise organizations
to avoid all of the complexity of having
to build data platforms inside of new
software as well as make it so that
whenever you have to do an integration
you can intercept that work and we
reframe that as a Liberation which is
basically don't integrate it from
systematic system B is liberate that
data by connecting it into a dataware
environment and then from that point
forward you can collaborate on that data
so liberate don't integrate so we have a
platform that's pretty powerful it has
some of the capabilities we've described
there's still lots more coming but yeah
that's that's what we do okay
well if listeners want to find out more
about what you're up to where should
they go two places one is asinji.com if
you want to check out our actual
commercial platform the other is
dataclaboration.org if you want to know
more about just the concepts behind this
and how to enable data collaboration and
not just to learn more about it but
we're looking for contributors as well
so there's an open environment the
collaborative intelligence Network you
can actually join in you can interact
with dataware you can use it to
basically further the cause so depending
on your interest check out one of those
two sources
great well Dan thank you so much for
joining me today on software engineering
radio thanks for having me this one this
is Jeff Doolittle for software
engineering radio thanks for listening
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se.radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under created Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening
[Music]